Finding Aid for the Lawrence Clark Powell Papers LSC.0229
UCLA Library Special Collections
Lawrence Clark Powell papers
1914-2001
UCLA Library Special Collections
Powell, Lawrence Clark
LSC.0229
105.5 Linear Feet (211 boxes and 22 oversize boxes.)
4 Audiovisual Carriers (4 audiocassettes)
Lawrence Clark Powell (1906-2001) joined the UCLA Library staff in 1938, became a UCLA Librarian (1944-61), director of the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library (1944-66), and the first Dean of the UCLA School of Library Service (1960). A prolific author, Powell's writings include books and articles on a variety of topics including literature, librarianship, the book trade, California history, and travel. The collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, galley proofs, photographs, tape recordings, books, and printed materials by and about Lawrence Clark Powell.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with the exception of boxes 137-227 which are restricted until 25 years following the death of Lawrence Clark Powell. These materials will be open for research beginning March 14, 2026. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed audiovisual materials. Audiovisual materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lawrence Clark Powell, 1965-.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9927229433606533
Biography
Powell was born September 3, 1906 in Washington, D.C.; his family moved to South Pasadena, California, 1910; BA, Occidental College, 1928; Ph.D., University of Dijon, France, 1932; worked at Jake Zeitlin's bookstore in Los Angeles, mid-1930s; graduated from library school, University of California at Berkeley, 1937; worked briefly at the Los Angeles Public Library; joined the UCLA Library staff in 1938; UCLA Librarian, 1944-61, and director of the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, 1944-66; became the first Dean, UCLA School of Library Service, 1960; when he retired from UCLA in 1966, the campus's main library was named in his honor; a prolific author, Powell's writings include books and articles on a variety of topics including literature, librarianship, the book trade, California history, and travel; professor-in-residence at the University of Arizona from 1971; awarded an Honorary Life Membership of the American Library Association, 1981. Powell died in 2001.
Biographical Narrative
Lawrence Clark Powell was born in Washington, D.C., on September 3, 1906. His parents, G. Harold and Gertrude (Clark) Powell, soon moved to Southern California, where Lawrence grew up. His early schooling was in South Pasadena, and he attended Occidental College in Los Angeles, where he received a bachelor's degree in English in 1928. Moving to France for his graduate studies, Lawrence Powell earned a Ph.D. at the University of Dijon in 1932, for work on Robinson Jeffers and his poetry. Soon after his return to the United States, Dr. Powell married Fay Ellen Shoemaker; they have two sons.
Although Lawrence Clark Powell knew that his main interest was in books, he had not yet discovered librarianship, and for several years he worked with booksellers in Los Angeles. During this period he helped Ward Ritchie and Jake Zeitlin, who had begun the Ward Ritchie and the Primavera Presses, to publish western books. Then he decided to go to the UC School of Librarianship at Berkeley, where in 1937 he received the certificate of librarianship.
Lawrence Clark Powell's first position after graduation was with the Los Angeles Public Library; he soon (1938) joined the UCLA library, however, with which he has been associated since. In 1944 Lawrence Clark Powell was appointed Director of the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, and in the same year he became Head Librarian of the UCLA Library. The Clark Library, specializing in books on English civilization of the 17th and early 18th centuries, grew from 16,000 volumes in 1934 to over 65,000 today, and the UCLA library as a whole went from 480,000 to 1,570,000 volumes during the period that Dr. Powell was at its head.
Due to Lawrence Clark Powell's efforts, in 1946 the library organized a department of Special Collections to house rare and valuable material. Dr. Powell's frequent book-hunting trips, such as the year spent in England (1951) in conjunction with a Guggenheim Fellowship, have enriched this department. As a result of Dr. Powell's activities UCLA obtained the noted Sadleir Collection of 19th-Century Fiction, as well as other important collections. Another project dear to the heart of UCLA's head librarian was the establishment of a School of Library Service on the UCLA campus. The school came into being in the fall of 1960, with Lawrence Clark Powell as its first dean. In June, 1961, Dr. Powell relinquished the title of University Librarian to Robert Vosper, continuing as Dean of the Library School and as Director of the Clark Library.
Lawrence Clark Powell is a vigorous proponent of a philosophy of librarianship stressing thorough knowledge of books and desire to serve the needs of the public rather than technological developments, or as he has called them, mechanical house-keeping techniques..
Using various means for diffusing his ideas on books and libraries, Lawrence Clark Powell has become known as an educator, a lecturer, and an author. In 1954 he spent a year as visiting professor of library science at Columbia University, and from 1955 to 1960 as Lecturer in English he taught a course called Libraries and Learning (English 195), at UCLA. 1960, of course, saw Dr. Powell as Dean of the new UCLA Library School.
Only a brief indication can be given here of the extent of Dr. Powell's speaking and writing. Among a number of distinguished speaking engagements can be noted the Randolph G. Adams Memorial Lectureship at the University of Michigan (1953), the library lectureship at the University of Tennessee (1954), and the annual lecture given at the meeting of the Library Association of Great Britain (at Harrogate, 1957). Dr. Powell has been heard in many radio broadcasts, including the Books I Like series he gave on KFAC (Los Angeles) in 1935.
A prolific author, Lawrence Clark Powell has written over 300 items: books, magazine articles, essays, book reviews, forewords and introductions to books, bibliographies, etc. He has made a significant contribution to the literature of the library profession, but he also writes for the book-minded public. His interests are reflected in the subjects that recur throughout his writings; these are history and travel, especially concerning the American Southwest, rare books, libraries and librarianship, the book trade, and book collecting.
As a measure of his involvement with the community, a few of the many organizations to which Lawrence Clark Powell has belonged can be cited. Dr. Powell has been a member of the American Library Association and many other such associations, president of the California Library Association in 1950, and president of the Bibliographical Society of America in 1954-55; he is a Phi Gamma Delta member, and belongs to the Zamorano Club (Los Angeles).
Dr. Powell has been recognized by Occidental College with the award of an honorary degree of Doctor of Letters (1955) and by the Carnegie Institute of Technology with the honorary title of Doctor of Humane Letters (1961). Juniata College, Huntingdon, Pennsylvania, awarded him this same degree in 1963.
The Lawrence Clark Powell Papers were given to the UCLA Department of Special Collections as a continuing gift of Dr. Powell, in 1950. The collection is a growing one, as new material is added from time to time. The collection consists of manuscripts with holograph corrections, copies of Lawrence Clark Powell's publications, bibliographies and reviews of his works, tape recordings of speeches, correspondence, records of classes he has taught and organizations to which he has belonged, articles about Dr. Powell, and personal memorabilia and juvenilia.
Additional information and papers of Lawrence Clark Powell can be found in the Powell Family Papers, Collection Number 230; in the Records of the Office of the Librarian, B18, Series 9; and in other entries under Powell, Lawrence Clark, in the Numbered Collections Catalogue.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, galley proofs, photographs, tape recordings, books, and printed materials by and about former UCLA Librarian Lawrence Clark Powell. Includes materials related to classes taught by Powell at the UCLA School of Library Service. Also includes materials and correspondence related to various literary figures, bibliophiles, and organizations such as Henry Miller, Dawson's Bookshop, Jake Zeitlin, and the Zamorano Club. Manuscripts for several of Powell's publications are in the collection as well.
Related Material
Powell Family Papers (Collection 230). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Related Oral Histories
The following oral histories are available through the UCLA Library Center for Oral History Research:
Looking Back at Sixty [oral history transcript] / Lawrence Clark Powell, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1973. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
The UCLA Library School [oral history transcript] / Lawrence Clark Powell and Andrew H. Horn, interviewees. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1962. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Interview of Lawrence Clark Powell (1973)
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Lawrence Clark Powell Papers (5 items).
Manuscripts for publication; Historians -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Authors -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Librarians -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Powell, Lawrence Clark -- Archives; University of California, Los Angeles. School of Library Service--Faculty -- Archives
- Philosopher Pickett
  - Research Material
    - Letters from Charles Edward Pickett to Various Persons, v.d.
      - 1846-1847. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - 1851-1857. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - 1872-1878. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letters to and from various persons, 1847-1848. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Charles Edward Pickett's Pamphlets, v.d.
      - 1856-1871. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - 1876-1880. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Charles Edward Pickett's Newspaper contributions, 1845-1882. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - News items and articles about Charles Edward Pickett, 1849-1962. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Charles Edward Pickett and the California Legislature, 1853-1878. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters, reminiscences and articles by and about various persons, 1844-1956. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous and photographs. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Research Notes
    - Outlines, bibliographies, etc. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Charles Edward Pickett geneology: Virginia, Tennessee and Overland Journey. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Charles Edward Pickett, v.d.
      - In: Oregon, San Francisco, Hawaii, Sonoma and Sutter's Fort., 1840s (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - In the: San Francisco and Sacramento., 1850s (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - In the: Sacramento and Los Angeles., 1860s (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - In the, 1870s-1880s. (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - As Professor and Pamphleteer. (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Annotated works. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Flumgudgeon Gazette. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Western American. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Manuscripts and Typescripts
    - Articles on the Flumgudgeon Gazette and the Western American by Lawrence Clark Powell. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Powell, Lawrence Clark. Philosopher Pickett.. (3rd draft)., (Original typescript) (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Scope and Contents note
      Bound with some correspondence.
  - Correspondence
    - Letters to Lawrence Clark Powell from Various Persons, v.d.
      - 1939. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - 1940-1949. (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - 1951. (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - 1952-. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Letters to and from various persons, 1941-1951. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Reviews, releases and clippings. (Box 3, Folder 6)
      re Powell's Philosopher Pickett.
    - Miscellaneous. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Publications
    - Articles by Lawrence Clark Powell:
      - The Western American--An Early California Newspaper. In Bibiographical Society of America Papers (4th Quarter), 1940. (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Flumgudgeon Gazette in 1845 Antedated The Spectator. In Oregon Historical Quarterly, June 1940. (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - The Remarkable Contempt Case of Philosopher Pickett. Interchange Fortnightly (vol.1, no.3), June 28, 1940. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Powell, Lawrence Clark. Philosopher Pickett, The Life and Writings of Charles Edward Pickett. Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California Press, 1942. (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Ghost In The Underblows
  - Autobiographical and Miscellaneous Notes
    - Notes by Alfred Young Fisher. (Box 4, Folder 1)
      For the preface to Ghost in the Underblows including some on D.H. Lawrence and Bertrand Russell.
    - Notes on the Ghost in the Underblows. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      re its relation to the Holy Bible by Lawrence Clark Powell.
      Also includes notes on Book 6 by Dow Parkes submitted for Prospectus to Ghost in the Underblows.
  - Manuscripts and Typescripts--Ghost in the Underblows
    - Ghost in the Underblows by Alfred Young Fisher. Dijon, [Published in Los Angeles, ]., 1931 1940 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Original Manuscript.
    - The Ghost in the Underblows... edited with an Introduction by Lawrence Clark Powell, 1938-1940.; (Bound in one volume) (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Editor's typescript with related material.
    - Ghost in the Underblows., (With holograph corrections) (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Typescript drafts of the Prospectus.
  - Other Manuscripts and Typescripts by Alfred Young Fisher
    - [Unpublished Sonnets], 1929.; (One manuscript notebook) (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Poems; written mostly in Dijon []., 1930- 1931; (Typescript drafts) (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - A Little Book of Preferences., (Typescript draft, 14 leaves) (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Eight Opinions of a.y.f. for m.f.k.f., (Typescript draft) (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Occasional Sonnets with an Introduction, v.d. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Shagbag on the Air Written for the Pleasure of Monk, Richman, and Goose by A.Y.F. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Galley Proofs and Layout Sheets
    - The Ghost in the Underblows. (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Galley Proofs and Layout Sheets.
    - Introduction to the Ghost in the Underblows., (5 leaves) (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Galley Proofs.
  - Correspondence
    - Letters to Lawrence Clark Powell from Alfred Young Fisher, v.d..
      re the editing and publication of Ghost...
      - 1937-1939. (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - 1940. (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - 1941 and n.d. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Letters to Alfred Young Fisher from various persons, 1940-1941 and n.d. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Letters to LCP from various persons, 1939-1940 and n.d. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Letters to the Ghost Publishing Company, West Los Angeles, California from various persons,, subscribing to copies of the Ghost., 1939-1940 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Letters to and from various persons, 1938-1941. (Box 6, Folder 7)
      re publication of the Ghost...
  - Miscellaneous
    - The Ghost Publishing Company, Los Angeles, []., 1940; ([10]pp.) (Box 6, Folder 8)
      A prospectus announcing the publication...of...The Ghost in the Underblows...
    - Reviews of The Ghost in the Underblows by Alfred Young Fisher []., 1940 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Photographs and miscellaneous. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Other Publications by Alfred Young Fisher
    - Note on Shakespeare's prose. In >Revue Anglo-Americaine ()., October 1931 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Occasional Verses. Privately printed in Dijon, 1931. (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Pages from the Ghost. Privately printed [Dijon], 1931. (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - A story of four poems. In The Symposium (vol.4, no.1), January 1933. (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - The mountain of Sleep; War's hesperides: Parts from the Ghost in the Underblows... in Fortnightly (vol.1, no.1). Agoura, California, October 15, 1934. (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Some Literary Allusions to T.S. Eliot's Ash Wednesday in Interchange (vol.1 no.2), June 14, 1940. (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Excerpts from the Ghost in the Underblows in Smith College Monthly., December 12, 1940. (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Nota sulla Fenice... in Inventario (vol.1, no.2), Estate, 1946. (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - An encounter. [n.p., ]., n.d.; ([12pp.]) (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - The Ghost in the Underblows
    - The Ghost in the Underblows. Los Angeles: Ward Ritchie Press, 1940. (Box 6, Folder 20)
      Imperfect copy.
      A Fragment by Alfred Young Fisher; Edited with an Introduction by LCP, Designed by Alvin Lustig.
      General note
      (p.9 misbound)
- Island of Books
  - Hoja Volante Articles
    - Hoja Volante articles by Lawrence Clark Powell, February 1948-December 1950.; (12 articles) (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Final typescript drafts submitted to the editor William Wilcox Robinson.
      Also, 2 letters to Robinson from Lawrence Clark Powell.
    - Return to France. In Pacific Spectator. Stanford, California, 1951.; ([6]pp.) (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Duplicate of 1st Galley Proof.
  - Books on Land
    - Books on Land and other essays from Hoja Volante by Lawrence Clark Powell. (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Clippings of Hoja Volante articles and 3 additional typescript drafts with holograph corrections.
    - Books on Land and other essays on collecting and reading by Lawrence Clark Powell., (Typescript) (Box 7, Folder 4)
      Draft with a holograph preface.
  - Island of Books
    - Island of Books. (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Galley proofs and layout sheets with holograph corrections.
    - Island of Books and other essays from Hoja Volante by Lawrence Clark Powell. (Box 7, Folder 6)
      Final draft, corrected from galley proof with layout instructions and publisher's corrections.
    - Prospecti, announcements, promotional material, etc. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Reviews in journals, newspapers, etc. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Letters to Lawrence Clark Powell from various persons, 1951-. (Box 7, Folder 9)
      re Island of Books.
  - Publication
    - Powell, Lawrence Clark. Island of Books. Los Angeles: Ward Ritchie Press, 1951. (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Powell, Lawrence Clark. Island of Books. Hoja Volante (no.20), August 1948. (Box 7, Folder 11)
- The Alchemy of Books
  - Manuscripts
    - The Alchemy of Books, June 30, 1952.; (14 leaves, Ozalid typescript) (Box 8, Folder 1)
      A speech given at the opening General Session of 71st Annual Conference of the American Library Association, Hotel Waldorf-Astoria, New York.
    - The Alchemy of Books. Los Angeles: Ward Ritchie Press, 1954. (Box 8, Folder 2)
      Publisher's corrected typescript draft with some holograph corrections.
  - Galley Proofs
    - The Alchemy of Books. Los Angeles: Ward Ritchie Press, 1954. (Box 8, Folder 3)
      Galley Proofs (1) with holograph and publisher's corrections.
    - The Alchemy of Books. Los Angeles: Ward Ritchie Press, 1954. (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Galley Proofs (2) with holograph and publisher's corrections.
    - The Alchemy of Books. Los Angeles: Ward Ritchie Press, 1954. (Box 9, Folder 1)
      Galley Proofs (3) with holograph and publisher's corrections.
  - Miscellaneous
    - American Library Association 71st Annual Conference. New York, 1952.; (3 leaves) (Box 9, Folder 2)
      [Press release re Lawrence Clark Powell's speech, The Alchemy of Books, delivered before the Association, June 30, 1952].
    - Reviews of Lawrence Clark Powell's book, The Alchemy of Books. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Publications
    - The Alchemy of Books; an Address at the First General Session of the New York Conference, in the ALA Bulletin (vol.46, no.8), June 30, 1952 September 1952. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - The Alchemy of Books; a few parts of the address given opening the General Session of the ALA on in the Antiquarian Bookman (vol.10, no.3), June 30, 1952 July 19, 1952. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - The Alchemy of Books, and Other Essays and Addresses on Books and Writers by Lawrence Clark Powell. Los Angeles: Ward Ritchie Press, 1954. (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - The Alchemy of Books, Bulletin of the School Library Association of California (vol.27, no.3), March 1956. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence relating to the publication and sale of Alchemy of Books, 1954-1959. (Box 9, Folder 8)
- J. Frank Dobie
  - Notes, Outlines and Sketches
    - Notes and outlines re J. Frank Dobie. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Notes and autobiographical sketch by J. Frank Dobie., (2 carbon copy typescripts, 6 leaves) (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Manuscripts and Typescripts
    - Various Manuscripts by J. Frank Dobie, 1953-1958.; (5 typescripts, 19 leaves) (Box 10, Folder 3)
      With holograph notes and miscellaneous corrections.
    - A Man Named Dobie by Lawrence Clark Powell., November 17, 1954.; (Holograph manuscript, 23 leaves) (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - A Man Named Dobie by Lawrence Clark Powell., (2 typescripts on sulfide bond, 10 leaves) (Box 10, Folder 5)
      With holograph corrections and revisions.
    - A Man Named Dobie by Lawrence Clark Powell., (8 leaves) (Box 10, Folder 6)
      Publisher's typescript with some holograph corrections.
    - A Texan Named Dobie; a Man Named Dobie revised for Books West Southwest., May 1956; (Carbon copy typescript, 6 leaves) (Box 10, Folder 7)
      With holograph corrections.
    - Dobie., (Typescript on sulfide bond, [9] leaves) (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - [J. Frank Dobie]., (Typescript, 16 leaves) (Box 10, Folder 9)
      With corrections.
    - Mr. Southwest., (17 leaves) (Box 10, Folder 10)
      Revised typescript of [J. Frank Dobie] with holograph corrections.
    - Mr. Southwest: J. Frank Dobie of Texas., (Carbon copy typescript, 15 leaves) (Box 10, Folder 11)
      With corrections and notes by J. Frank Dobie.
    - Mr. Southwest: J. Frank Dobie of Texas., (15 leaves) (Box 10, Folder 12)
      Publisher's typescript.
    - Other Manuscripts about J. Frank Dobie., (Two carbon copy typescripts, 5 leaves) (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Galley Proofs
    - A Man Named Dobie., (3 leaves) (Box 10, Folder 14)
      Galley Proofs and layout sheets.
  - Correspondence
    - Letters from J. Frank Dobie to Lawrence Clark Powell, 1953-1957. (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Letters from J. Frank Dobie to Lawrence Clark Powell, 1958- n.d. (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Letters from J. Frank Dobie to various persons, 1953-1961. (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Letters from Lawrence Clark Powell to J. Frank Dobie, 1953-1959. (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Letters from Lawrence Clark Powell to various persons, 1956-. (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Letters from various persons to Lawrence Clark Powell, 1954-. (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Letters to and from various persons, 1954-1957. (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Photographs. (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous. (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Publications
    - Dobie, J. Frank, []. Forty-four Range Country Books., 1941; (Mimeographed typescript, 8 leaves) (Box 10, Folder 24)
    - Dobie, J. Frank. A Librarian and Books. In San Antonio Light, Sunday, December 19, 1954. (Box 10, Folder 25)